Hans Hofmann
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- School of Fine Arts Records, 1915-1965, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 4-5; 2.0 linear ft.; Reels 5804-5806)
  A small cache of records concerning Hofmann's school in Munich is supplemented by photographs (Series 6) containing views of Hans Hofmann with students during the 1920s, including some taken during a summer session in Capri, circa 1925. Travel photographs from the same period may have been taken while teaching summer courses in Europe. An undated, unidentified photograph of an exhibition installation in Germany may be school-related.
  Records concerning Hofmann's schools in New York City and Provincetown, Mass., consist of administrative, financial, student, and miscellaneous records. Material postdating the schools' 1958 closings consist of letters of inquiry from prospective students and requests from former students for transcripts or recommendations. Additional letters from former students are with Correspondence (Series 1).
  For the large part, student records were created and maintained by registrar James Gahagan and his staff. Student ledgers note date of first entry into day and evening courses and tuition paid. A variety of other information is also included in the student ledgers: number of class hours and fees for supplies are entered in vol. 1, vols. 2 and 3 record advance payments for summer school, lists of monitors and scholarships are included in vols. 3 and 4, and a partial roster of summer school students appears in vol. 4. Requests for transcripts and recommendations are addressed to Hofmann who appears to have handled these matters directly.
  Among the miscellaneous items are a gouache painting by student Trude Baumann, and class notes of Dorothy G. Hales/Dorothy H. Gary.
  This series is divided into 2 subseries:
  2.1: Munich, 1915-1933
  2.2: New York City and Provincetown, circa 1936-1965, undated
  - Munich, 1915-1933, 2.1:
    - Prospectuses, 1915-1916, 1933 (Box 4, Reel 5804)
    - Financial Record, 1925 (Box 4, Reel 5804)
    - "Italian Schools of Painting: The Renaissance in Italy," 1923 (Box 4, Reel 5804)
  - New York City and Provincetown, Mass., circa 1936-1965, undated, 2.2:
    - Administrative Records, 2.2.1:
      - Accreditation, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Reel 5804)
      - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1945, 1952 (Box 4, Reel 5804)
      - Immigration and Naturalization Service-Approval of School and General Correspondence, 1953- 1964, undated (Box 4, Reel 5804)
      - Immigration and Naturalization Service-re: Foreign Students (A-Z, by year), 1953-1957, (2 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5804)
      - Inquiries from Prospective Students, 1956-1965, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5804-5805)
      - Model Bookings and Payments, 1955/56 and Summer 1957 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Office Procedure and Responsibilities, undated (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Prospectuses, circa 1936-1955/56, undated (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Veterans Administration, 1947-1953, undated (Box 4, Reel 5805)
    - Financial Records, 2.2.2:
      - Expense Statements, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Income, summer 1956 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
    - Student Records, 2.2.3:
      - Student Ledger, vol. 1: A-Z (disbound), 1946-1952, (2 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Student Ledger, vol. 2: 1952/53-1953/54 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Student Ledger, vol. 3: 1954/55 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Student Ledger vol. 4: 1955/56 (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Registration and Payment Records, 1952/53-1955/56, (1 folder and 1 card file) (Box 4, Reel 5805)
      - Summer School Registration and Payment Records, 1953-1958, (7 folders and 1 card file) (Box 5, Reel 5805)
      - Requests for Transcripts and Recommendations (A-Z), 1947-1965, (13 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5805-5806)
    - Miscellaneous, 2.2.4:
      - Student Artwork, undated (Box 5, Reel 5806)
      - Student Notes, 1955-1956, undated (Box 5, Reel 5806)
- Writings, circa 1904-1965, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 6-7, 20-21; 2.6 linear ft.; Reels 5806-5808 and unfilmed)
  This series includes published and unpublished manuscripts, drafts, revisions, and notes by Hofmann and other authors, organized by type-books, articles and essays, etc. Hans Hofmann wrote extensively about his philosophy of painting, about himself as a teacher and an artist, and about modern art. Writings by other authors are mainly about Hofmann and modern art.
  Books, arranged alphabetically by title, include manuscripts, drafts, and revisions. Considered Hofmann's most important text, Das Malerbuch: Form und Farbe in Gestaltung, circa 1904-1952[?], is an instructional primer begun in Paris circa 1904 and added to over many years. It remains unpublished. An English translation, Creation in Form and Color, was made by Glenn Wessels in 1931. Peggy Huck's translation, The Supersensitory Origin of Painting, was completed in 1931. After microfilming was completed, several versions of Das Malerbuch and the two English translations were received from the Renate, Hans and Maria Hofmann Trust in 2006. Search for the Real and Other Essays, was issued in 1948 to accompany Hofmann's retrospective exhibition at the Addison Gallery of American Art, Andover, Mass., the first one-man show of an Abstract Expressionist organized by a museum.
  Articles and essays consist of published and unpublished manuscripts arranged alphabetically by title, with untitled items alphabetized by first line. Among them are the constituent essays of Search for the Real and Other Essays: "The Search for the Real in the Visual Arts," "Sculpture," "On the Aims of Art;" and "Plastic Creation."
  Notes, outlines, and some complete texts of speeches are arranged chronologically. Miscellaneous writings are shorter, informative, mostly unpublished pieces written between 1944 and 1960. Untitled items are alphabetized by first line. Representative titles include: "I am Often Asked to Explain My Work," "A Reply to the Demand to Name some of My Students that have come Into Prominence," and "About the relation of students and teachers." Hofmann revised 5 manuscripts ("Untitled, in German, undated") by literally cutting and pasting portions onto very long sheets which were then rolled tightly for storage. Over the years, the glue dried out and the scrolls came apart; fortunately, most sections were numbered sequentially, so their order could be reconstructed fairly well prior to microfilming.
  Among the notes and lists are notes on works of art concerning "Construction," "Magenta and Blue," the Chiamabote mural, and New York School of Printing mosaic. Lists of paintings include works to be exhibited at Galerie Maeght, Paris, Mirski Gallery, Boston, and Whitney Museum; works to be framed; and works to be shipped.
  Writings by other authors are mostly unpublished articles, essays, and reviews arranged alphabetically by author. An untitled piece by C. Z., most likely Carl Zigrosser, was written in response to an article about the psychlogy of Picaasso's art by Carl Jung. Unsigned items include a review of Camille Pisarro: Letters to his Son Lucien, ed. John Rewald, undated; review of Hofmann exhibitions at the 67 Gallery, 1945, and Galerie Maeght, 1949.
  3.1: By Hofmann, 1928-1965, undated
  3.2: By Other Authors, circa 1904-1964, undated
  - By Hofmann, 1928-1965, undated, 3.1:
    - Books, A-Z, 3.1.1:
      - Das Malerbuch: Form und Farbe in der Gestaltung, (see also Boxes 20-21) (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Memorandum, 1949 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Early Drafts, circa 1931 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Drafts and Notes, 1949 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - Das Malerbuch[?] (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part I "Definition of form," 1952[?] (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part II a) "Nature in 'objective'experience" b) "Nature in 'plastic' experience" and c) "Nature in 'visual' experience" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part III a) "Light" and b) "Relationship of form, light and color" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part IV "The picture plane" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part V "Colour as a plastic means" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part VI "The mind" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Draft, Part VII "Composition" (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Chapter, "Bild formende gesetze," undated (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Chapter, "Entwicklungs-Plan I," 1929[?] (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Chapter, "Entwicklungs-Plan II," undated (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - Intended Addition, "The object in the visual arts-its function in three-dimensional reality and its two-dimensional pictorial realization," 1951 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
        - "Picture material for Book, undated (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - The Painter and His Problems-A Manual Dedicated to Painting, 1963, (2 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - Search for the Real and Other Essays, 1947-1948, (3 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5806)
    - Das Malerbuch: Form und Farbe in der Gestalatung - Manuscripts in German, (see also Boxes 6 and 21) (Box 20 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
      - "Based on the first book written in California," 1934, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
      - "Copy of the German original, 1948,", (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
      - Manuscript, Autumn, 1948, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
      - Edited Manuscript, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
    - Das Malerbuch: Form und Farbe in der Gestalatung - English Translations, (see also Boxes 6 and 20) (Box 21 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
      - "English Original" (translated by Peggy Huck as The Supersensitory Origin of Painting), 1953 (Box 21 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
      - "The Painter's Book, First English translation by Glenn Wessels" (Creation in Form and Color), 1931, (2 folders) (Box 21 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
      - Illustrations (original drawings, photostats and negatives of diagrams, photographs [captions and notations in both English and German]), undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
    - Articles and Essays, 3.1.2:
      - "The Color Problem in Pure painting-Its Creative Origin," 1955, undated (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "The Creative Act-Gesture and meaning," undated (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Hawthorne-The Painter: An Appreciation," 1952 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Homage to Alfred Maurer," 1950 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "The Mystification of the Two- and Three-Dimensional in theVisual Arts," 1946 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "On the Aims of Art," 1931-1932 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Painting and Culture," 1931 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Plastic Creation," 1932 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Plastisches Gestalten" (See: "Plastic Creation), 1932 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Quality??? What is It-What does it mean in the visual arts?," [1951?] (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "I. The Resurrection of the Plastic Arts; II. The Mystery of Creative Relations," 1953 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "Sculpture," 1933 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "The Search for the 'Real' in the Visual Arts," 1947-1948 (Box 6, Reel 5806)
      - "The Search for the 'Real' in the visual Arts," (cont'd.), 1947-1948 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Die Welt und die Kunst," 1965 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Ziele der Kunst" (See: "On the Aims of Art") (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - Untitled, 1928-1950, undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
    - Talks and Lectures, 3.1.3:
      - 1930: University of Minnesota Art Department (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1931: Berkeley Women's City Club; University of California, Berkeley, "Lectures on Plastic Painting," and untitled lectures (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1938: Lecture notes including: "Kosmos and cosmic creation on a picture plane," "Life," "Natur" (sic), "Movement of space," "Movement of Volumes" (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1938-39: Provincetown lectures, "The Laws of the Picture Plane" (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1939-40: Notes and texts including: "The realm of the unconscious" and Picasso" (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1940: Untitled lecture delivered in Provincetown, July 27 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1941: Address delivered Feb. 16 at Riverside Museum symposium on Abstract Art held during the 1941 Annual American Abstract Artists' Exhibition (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1949: "What Is an Artist?" delivered July 3, "American Art Today," "American Art versus French Art," and "Protest Against Ostrich Attitude in the Arts" (with Fritz Bultman) (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1950: Studio 35 Round Table; texts and notes for Provincetown Art Association talks, untitled (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1951: "About Education in General and Art Education in Particular," Provincetown Art Association, August 13 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1952: "Photography as a Creative means," Provincetown Art Association, August 12; remarks recorded for Sam Feinstein's film (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - 1962: "A speech delivered at the Inauguration of the Hopkins Center, Dartmouth College, Hanover, New Hampshire, November 17, 1962 by Hans Hofmann" (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - undated: "Point and Line," "Artistic Childrenswork," "Hofmann Lectures No. Three to Eleven [10 and 11 lacking]," texts of several untitled talks, and notes for introducing Hofmann (Box 6, Reel 5807)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 3.1.4:
      - "About Art education and my approach toward it," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "About critics," 1956 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "About Jackson Pollack and myself," 1956 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "About myself, my work, my school," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "About the relation of students and teachers," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "About the subject mater (in pictorial creation)," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Advanced Education in Art," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "An answer to a Question," 1951 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "An Answer to My Critics," 1944 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Architecture and pictorial art," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Art and Art appreciation," 1953 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Art and Life," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Collected writing on Art," 1958 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Colour," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "The creative process-its physical and metaphysical performing," 1956 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Falsification of History," [1959] (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "The following is a condenced (sic) reformulation of a statement made by me to my students dating back to 1938," 1960 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "For Clarification of history I speak (reluctantly) of myself," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Form im simme der Gertabtung," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "In Answer to a Question," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Life," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "The magic of painting," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "My aim-in answer to repeated questioning," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "My Artistic Creed-A Statement," 1952 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Nature and Art-Controversy and Misconcept," 1957 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Nature as Experience and Its Pictorial Realization," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "A New Concept for Mosaics of Our Time," 1956 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Notes on Art," 1950 (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "The Offense in Pictorial Art," undated (Box 6, Reel 5807)
      - "Pictorial Function of Colours," 1950 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "Preface for catalogue for Hofmann exhibit, Berkeley, California," July 30, 1931 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "A Reply to the Demand to Name Some of My Students Who Have Come into Prominence," 1956 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "Space and pictorial life," undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "Space pictorially realized through the intrinsic faculty of the colours to express volume," 1951 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "Spannungs Bezichungen," undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Statement for Abstract and Surrealist Art in America by Sidney Janis, 1944 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Statements for Contemporary American Painting, University of Illinois, 1951 and 1952 (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "The teaching of Hans Hofmann," undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "This is the answer to a repeated refusal of acceptance of my work to the permanent collection of the museum of modern art," undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - "What is Life," undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Untitled, A-Z (by first line), 1946-1961, undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Untitled (5 folders; in German), undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Fragments, undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
    - Poems, 3.1.5:
      - Poems, 1944-1959, undated (Box 7, Reel 5807)
      - Poems, cont'd., 1944-1959, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Poems to Maria Hofmann, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Notes and Lists, 3.1.6:
      - Notebooks,(2 vols.), "Farbe" and untitled, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Notes on Works of Art, 1949-1956 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - List of Paintings, 1949-1962, undated, (7 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Lists of Photographs given to William Seitz, circa 1950 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Miscellaneous Lists, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - By Other Authors, circa 1910-1964, undated, 3.2:
    - About Hofmann and Modern Art, 3.2.1:
      - Gasquet, Joachim. "What He Said to Me. The Motive," translation from an article in L'amour del'Art, December 1921 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Graham. "The Case of Mr. Picasso," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Greenberg, Clement. Lecture on Hofmann and exhibition reviews, 1945-1947, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Gris, Juan. "Concerning the Possibilities of Painting," lecture at the Sorbonne, circa 1910 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Haecker, Theodore. "Was ist Kultur?," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Holzmann. "American Abstract Artists, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Hunter, Sam. "Hans Hofmann," 1963 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Kaldis, Aristodimos Melandinos. "Le Maire par Excellence: Hans Hofmann," 1962 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Kaprow, Allan. "Hans Hofmann," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Larguier, Leo. "Le Diamanche avec Cézanne," [extract], undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Matisse, Henri. "Henri Matisse Speaks About Painting," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Mondrian, Piet. "Toward the True Vision of Reality," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Stout, Myron J. "Statement," undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Thurston, Carl H. P. "How Movement is Painted," from How We Look at Pictures, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Wessels, Glenn. "On the Aesthetic Content of Pictures, a lecture given before the Pacific Arts Association and the State Conference on Art Called by the State Board of Education in California...," April 1931 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Williams, Tennessee. "An Appreciation," from Women: A Collaboration of Artists and Writers, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - C. Z. [Carl Zigrosser?], Untitled, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
      - Unsigned, 1945-1960, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Poems, 3.2.2:
      - Poems, 1941-1964, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
- Financial Records, 1927-1966, undated, Series 4:; (Box 7; 0.5 linear ft.; Reel 5808)
  Financial records, filed alphabetically by folder title, consist mainly of banking records, and tax returns and supporting documentation. Additional tax records are among the records regarding Hans Hofmann's Estate (Series 9). In addition, there are statements of assets and liabilities and a few subject files concerning financial matters.
  - American Express Company, 1961-1967 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Assets and Liabilities, 1946-1966, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Banks (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Bayerische Vereinsbank, 1962-1965 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - The Bowery Savings Bank, 1963 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank (checking account), 1965 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank (custody account), 1965-1966 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank (stocks and savings), 1965-1966 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Ehlinger & Cie, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - First National Bank of Cape Cod, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Gothaer Lebensversicherungs-bank, 1927-1937 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Manufacturers Hanover Trust, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - New York Savings Bank, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
    - Various Savings Accounts, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Hayes Storage Invoices and Contracts, 1942-1947 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - House Expenses, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Receipts and Miscellaneous Records (in German), undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Social Security, 1955-1963, undated (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - Taxes, 1930-1966, undated, (7 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5808)
  - University of California, Financial Standing with, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Reel 5808)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1906-1966, undated, Series 5:; (Box 8; 0.75 linear ft.; Reels 5808-5809)
  Miscellaneous Records are organized into a number of categories, most of which include just a few items. Each folder is arranged chronologically.
  The early portion of the 1932 appointment book records Hofmann's business and personal expenses. Artwork by Hofmann consists of 4 sketches and are in ink and pencil and 3 oversize block prints of flat, red shapes (one is the numeral 5).
  Among the miscellaneous items included with biographical information are Hofmann's permit to paint in the Luxembourg Gardens issued in 1911, power of attorney, a building permit, automobile registration, galley proof of entry for Who's Who in the East (10th edition), and Hofmann's calling card. Additional wills are with the miscellaneous Estate Records (Series 9).
  This series is divided into 7 subseries:
  5.1: Addresses, circa 1930-1966, undated
  5.2: Appointment Books, 1932, 1960, 1966
  5.3: Artifacts, undated
  5.4: Artwork by Hofmann, undated
  5.5: Biographical Information, 1883-1966, undated
  5.6: Interview Transcripts, 1952-1966
  5.7: Sales Records, 1946-19965, undated
  - Addresses, circa 1930-1966, undated, 5.1:
    - Address Books (7 vols.), circa 1930-1966, (2 folders) (Box 8, Reel 5808-5809)
    - Names and Addresses, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
  - Appointment Books, 1932, 1960, 1966, 5.2:
    - Appointment Books (3 vols.), 1932, 1960, 1966 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
  - Artifacts, undated, 5.3:
    - Leather Wallet, undated (Box 8, Reel unfilmed)
    - Photogravure Blocks containing images of works of art and classes in session, undatedundated, (3 folders) (Box 8, Reel unfilmed)
  - Artwork by Hofmann, undated, 5.4:
    - Sketches, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Block Prints, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
  - Biographical Information, 1883-1966, undated, 5.5:
    - Bibliography of Writings on and by Hofmann, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Biographical Notes and Chronologies, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Birth Certificates, 1914-1941 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Hofmann Family (prayer card for Ines Hofmann,1883-1937), 1937, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Immigration and Naturalization Papers of Hans Hofmann, 1933-1943 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Immigration and Naturalization Papers of Maria Hofmann, 1937-1943, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Marriage Certificates, 1924, 1965 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Medical Notes, 1966, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1911-1964, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Wills, 1951, 1963 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Wolfegg Family Documents (in German), 1906, 1933 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1952-1966, 5.6:
    - Transcript of Interview with Hans Sahl, 1952 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Transcript of Interview with Paul Segnitz, 1957 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Transcript of Interview with Irma Jaffe for the Archives of American Art, 1966 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
  - Sales Records, 1946-1965, undated, 5.7:
    - Prices, 1961-1965 (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Private Sales, 1946-1957, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
    - Sales, 1949-1957, undated (Box 8, Reel 5809)
- Photographs, circa 1925-1966, undated, Series 6:; (Boxes 9-10; 1.25 linear ft.; Reel 5809)